<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<chapter id="wicket.installation">
	<title>Installation</title>
	<para>
		The seam-wicket-api.jar should be placed in the web application library folder. If you are using 
    <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</ulink> as your build tool, you can add the
		following dependency to your pom.xml file:
	</para>
	<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
	<groupId>org.jboss.seam.wicket</groupId>
	<artifactId>seam-wicket-api</artifactId>
	<version>${seam-wicket-version}</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>	
	<tip>
		<para>Replace ${seam-wicket-version} with the most recent or appropriate version of Seam Wicket.</para>			
	</tip>
  <para>
    You must also bootstrap Weld according to your environment.  As Wicket is normally used in a servlet (non-JavaEE) environment,
		this is most easily accomplished using the Weld Servlet integration, described in the <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.org/weld/reference/latest/en-US/html/environments.html">Weld Reference Guide</ulink>.
	</para>
	<para>
		You must extend org.jboss.seam.wicket.SeamApplication rather than org.apache.wicket.protocol.http.WebApplication.  In 
    addition: 
	</para>
			<itemizedlist>
     <listitem> if you override newRequestCycleProcessor to return your own IRequestCycleProcessor subclass, you must instead override 
 			getWebRequestCycleProcessorClass() and return the class of your processor, and your processor must extend SeamWebRequestCycleProcessor</listitem>
		 <listitem> if you override newRequestCycle to return your own RequestCycle subclass, you must make that subclass extend SeamRequestCycle.</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
	<para>
    If you can't extend SeamApplication, for example if you use an alternate Application superclass for which you do not control the source, 
		you can duplicate the three steps SeamApplication takes, i.e. return a SeamWebRequestCycleProcessor NonContextual instance in 
		newRequestCycleProcessor, return a SeamRequestCycle instance in newRequestCycle, and add a SeamComponentInstantiationListener 
		with addComponentInstantiationListener.
	</para>
</chapter>
